Guide to the Langdon Gilkey Papers 1921-2004
University of Chicago Library
- Series IV: Writings and Research
  - “Scripture, History, and the Quest for Meaning,” 1980 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - “The Khalsa Goes West,” 1980 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - “The Religious and Theological Dimensions of History,” 1980 (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - “Can Art fill the Vacuum?” 1981 (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - “How My Mind is Changing,” 1981 (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - “Meditation on Death and its Relation to Life,” 1981 (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - “Secularization,” 1981 (Box 13, Folder 12)
  - Testimony, McLean v Arkansas, 1981 (Box 13, Folder 13)
  - “The New Watershed in Theology,” 1981 (Box 13, Folder 14)
  - “Theology for a Time of Troubles,” 1981 (Box 13, Folder 15)
  - “The Protestant View of Sin,” 1981 (Box 13, Folder 16)
  - “The Roles of the Descriptive or Historical and of the Normative in Our Work,” 1981 (Box 13, Folder 17)
  - “The Vocation of the Theologies,” 1981 (Box 13, Folder 18)
  - Writings, 1981-1982 (Box 13, Folder 19)
  - “Creationism: the Roots of the Conflict,” 1982 (Box 13, Folder 20)
  - “Free Will and Evil: A Christian View in Response to Professor Abe’s Paper,” 1982-86 (Box 13, Folder 21)
  - Review, Nishitani, Religion and Nothingness, circa 1982 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Notes on Keiji Nishitani, 1982-1986 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - “The Creationist Controversy,” 1982 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - “The Political Meaning of Silence,” 1982 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - “Religion and Science in an Advanced Scientific Culture,” 1983-1987 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Testimony and Correspondence related to Mueller v Allen, 1983 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - “Theological Frontiers: Implications for Bioethics,” 1983 (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - “The Paradigm Shift in Theology,” 1983 (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - “The Relevance of Luther Today,” 1983 (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - “Culture and Religions Belief,” 1984 (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - “Events, Meaning, and the Current Tasks of Theology,” 1984 (Box 14, Folder 11)
  - Notes, 1984-1987 (Box 14, Folder 12)
  - Notes on Nature, 1984-1988 (Box 14, Folder 13)
  - Papers and Notes on Philosophy and Religion, 1984-1985 (Box 14, Folder 14)
  - Papers on Science, Theology, and Cosmology, 1984-1985 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Review, Medawar, The Limits of Science, 1984 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - “The Christian Understanding of Suffering,” 1984 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - “The Meaning of Jesus the Christ,” 1984 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - “Theology of Culture and Christian Ethics,” 1984 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - “Denying the Image,” 1985 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Lectures on Science and Theology, circa 1985 (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - “Plurality and its Theological Implications,” 1985 (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - Proposal for A Handbook of Contemporary Christian Theologies, circa 1985 (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - “Reinhold Niebuhr as Political Theologian,” 1985-1986 (Box 15, Folder 10)
  - “Religion and Culture: A Protestant Problem,” 1985 (Box 15, Folder 11)
  - “Religion and Public Policy,” 1985 (Box 15, Folder 12)
  - Speeches in China (Box 15, Folder 13)
  - “The Creationist Issue: A Theologian’s View,” circa 1985 (Box 15, Folder 14)
  - “The Misunderstanding of the Image: Idealization,” 1985 (Box 15, Folder 15)
  - “The Pastoral Vocation in a Plural World,” 1985 (Box 15, Folder 16)
  - “A Retrospective Glance at My Work,” 1986 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Articles and notes on Abe Masao and the Kyoto School, 1986-1989 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - “Basic Faith and the Special Traditions,” 1986 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - “Comments on Practical Theology,” 1986 (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Review, Masao, Zen and Western Thought, 1986 (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - “The Promise of Dialogue,” 1986 (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - “Ethics,” 1987 (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - “Nature as the Image of God,” 1987 (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - Notes on Søren Kierkegaard, up to 1987 (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - Notes, Religion, and Science Conference, 1987 (Box 16, Folder 10)
  - “Religion and Science in an Advance Scientific Culture,” 1987 (Box 16, Folder 11)
  - Reply to Reviews of Creationism on Trial, 1987 (Box 16, Folder 12)
  - Review, Fox, Reinhold Niebuhr, 1987 (Box 16, Folder 13)
  - Review, Tanabe, Philosophy as Metanoetics, 1987 (Box 16, Folder 14)
  - “Science, Power, and the Ambiguity of History,” 1987 (Box 16, Folder 15)
  - “Tillich and the Kyoto School,” 1987 (Box 16, Folder 16)
  - “Whatever Happened to Immanuel Kant?” 1987 (Box 16, Folder 17)
  - “Augustine: Symbol and Source,” 1988 (Box 16, Folder 18)
  - “Biology, Ethics, and Theology,” 1988 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - “Forgotten Traditions in the Clergy’s Self-Understanding,” 1988 (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - “Fundamentalism and Science,” 1988 (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - “Fundamentalism and Science,” Second Copy, 1988 (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Hong Kong Visit, 1988 (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Lectures and Talks on Nature, Creationism, Science, and the Ethics, 1988-1990 (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - “The Need for a Liberal Education in a Scientific Culture,” 1988 (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - “Theodicy and Plurality,” 1988 (Box 17, Folder 8)
  - “The Principle of Order in the West,” 1988 (Box 17, Folder 9)
  - Criterion, Volume 28 (Box 17, Folder 10)
  - “Nature, Reality, and the Sacred,” 1989 (Box 17, Folder 11)
  - Notes on Science, Religion, and Nature, 1989-1991 (Box 17, Folder 12)
  - “Report on Christian Theological Seminary,” 1989 (Box 17, Folder 13)
  - “Tenabe and the Philosophy of Religion,” 1989 (Box 17, Folder 14)
  - “The Influence of Science on Theology,” 1989 (Box 17, Folder 15)
  - “Theological Comments on Job,” 1989 (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - “The Pluralism of Religions,” 1989 (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Articles for The New Handbook of Christian Theology, 1990 (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - “Assessment of David Tracy’s Plurality and Ambiguity, 1990 (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - “Caring for Creation: The Roles of Religion and Science,” 1990 (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Convocation Speech at Princeton Theological Seminary, 1990 (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - “Cosmos, Creationism, and Consciousness,” 1990 (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - “Human Existence, Selfishness, and Altruism,” 1990 (Box 18, Folder 8)
  - “Nature, the Human, and God,” 1990 (Box 18, Folder 9)
  - “The Church as a Theological Entity,” 1990 (Box 18, Folder 10)
  - “The Congregation as a Religious Community,” 1990 (Box 18, Folder 11)
  - “The Congregation as a Religious Community, Part II,” 1991 (Box 18, Folder 12)
  - “Three Lectures on Science and Religion,” circa 1990 (Box 18, Folder 13)
  - “To Karl-Hans,” 1990 (Box 18, Folder 14)
  - “What of Value does Religion have to say to Science?” 1990 (Box 18, Folder 15)
  - “Christian Faithfulness: Culture as Ally and Enemy,” 1991 (Box 18, Folder 16)
  - Conference Materials, SETI, 1991-1994 (Box 18, Folder 17)
  - Eric Fichner Files, 1991 (Box 18, Folder 18)
  - Glassman, “Comments on Prof. Langdon Gilkey’s Theology and the Life Sciences,” 1991 (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Lectures at the Newman Theological College, 1991 (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - “Nature and Religion,” 1991 (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Paul Tillich: a new Catholic Assessment, drafts, correspondence, and other materials, 1991-1993 (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - “Problems and Potentialities of Protestant Spirituality,” 1991 (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - “The Life Sciences and Theology,” 1991-1992 (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - TV Series, “Space, Time, and God,” 1991 (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - Vatican Observatory Conference, Rome, 1991 (Box 19, Folder 8)
  - “Creation Order and Compassion,” 1992 (Box 19, Folder 9)
  - Lecture at Lambuth University, 1992 (Box 19, Folder 10)
  - Lectures on Tillich at Universite Laval, Quebec, 1992 (Box 19, Folder 11)
  - “New Directions,” 1992 (Box 19, Folder 12)
  - Reports on NASA’s HRMS Project, 1992-1993 (Box 19, Folder 13)
  - “Speaking of God in Our American Culture,” 1992 (Box 19, Folder 14)
  - “A Ramble on a Road Taken,” 1993 (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - “Beginnings and Endings,” 1993 (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - “Catholic Elements in Tillich’s Technology,” 1993 (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - Essays by Holmes Rolston III, 1993 (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - List of “Addresses on Religion and Science in the Light of the Creation issue,” 1993 (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - “Nature as the Image of God,” 1993 (Box 20, Folder 6)
  - Nature, Science, and the Sacred, drafts and related materials, 1993 (Box 20, Folder 7)
  - Drafts and Notes for Chapter VIII of Nature, Science, and the Sacred, 1993 (Box 20, Folder 8)
  - “The God of Nature,” 1993 (Box 20, Folder 9)
  - “Nature, Religion, and the Sacred,” circa 1994 (Box 20, Folder 10)
  - Review, Hefner, The Human Factor, 1994 (Box 20, Folder 11)
  - “The Christian, the University, and the Challenge of Ecology,” 1994 (Box 20, Folder 12)
  - Raymond Brady Williams, “Swaminarayan Hindu Temple of Glen Ellyn,” circa 1994 (Box 20, Folder 13)
  - “An Open Letter to Christians on the Religious Right,” 1995 (Box 20, Folder 14)
  - “Plurality and its Theological Implications,” circa 1995 (Box 20, Folder 15)
  - “The Flight from Reason,” 1995 (Box 20, Folder 16)
  - Lecture at Brigham Young University, 1996 (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - “The Religious Right,” 1996 (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - Articles by Davidson Loehr, 1997-1998 (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - Kyle A Pasewark Files, 1997 (Box 21, Folder 4)
  - “Lay Leadership Institute,” Program, circa, 1997 (Box 21, Folder 5)
  - Sermon at Rockefeller Memorial Chapel, 1998 (Box 21, Folder 6)
  - “The Crisis of Christianity in North America,” 1998 (Box 21, Folder 7)
  - “A Short Essay on Creationism and National Security,” 1999 (Box 21, Folder 8)
  - “American Theology since Niebuhr and Tillich,” 1999 (Box 21, Folder 9)
  - “An Introduction to Tillich,” 1999-2000 (Box 21, Folder 10)
  - “Reinhold Niebuhr,” 1999 (Box 21, Folder 11)
  - Sermonettes and Lectures in Japan, 1999 (Box 21, Folder 12)
  - “The Meaning and Relevance of Creation,” 1999 (Box 21, Folder 13)
  - “The Religious Situation at the End of the Century,” 199 (Box 21, Folder 14)
  - “The Theology of Nature,” 1999 (Box 21, Folder 15)
  - On Niebuhr, related materials, 1999-2001 (Box 21, Folder 16)
  - “An Introduction to Tillich,” 2000 (Box 21, Folder 17)
  - “History and Theology,” 2000 (Box 21, Folder 18)
  - “Human Nature and Myth in the Age of Science,” 2000 (Box 21, Folder 19)
  - Notes on Creationism, circa 2000 (Box 21, Folder 20)
  - Notes on Tillich and Niebuhr, circa 2000 (Box 21, Folder 21)
  - Notes, “Tillich, Myth, and Existence,” 2000 (Box 21, Folder 22)
  - “Community: Essential, Dangerous, and Creative,” 2001 (Box 21, Folder 23)
  - “The Meaning and Relevance of Creation,” 2001 (Box 21, Folder 24)
  - “Comments on ‘Constructing and Testing Theological Models,’” 2002 (Box 21, Folder 25)
  - “Reinhold Niebuhr, Paul Tillich, and the Theological of Culture,” 2002 (Box 21, Folder 26)
  - Lectures at the Highlands Institute for American Religious and Philosophical Thought, 2003 (Box 21, Folder 27)
  - “Society and Politics in the Early Niebuhr,” 2003 (Box 21, Folder 28)
  - “Secularism, Fundamentalism, and the Religious Dimension,” 2004 (Box 21, Folder 29)
  - “Arete” Articles, N.D. (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - Draft, unidentified typescript, N.D. (Box 22, Folder 2)
  - Folder “Footnotes,” N.D. (Box 22, Folder 3)
  - Papers, N.D. (Box 22, Folder 4)
- Series V: Audio-Visual
  - Photographs of Langdon Gilkey, 1934-1980 (Box 22, Folder 5)
  - Framed Photograph, circa. 1970 (Box 22, Folder 6)
  - Photographs, circa 1971 (Box 22, Folder 7)
- Series VI: Restricted
  This series consists of student grades, recommendations, and other evaluative records, as well as college and graduate school papers of Gilkey himself. Folders dedicated to particular students are ordered alphabetically and other folders chronologically. Materials are restricted for eighty years after the date of record creation.
  - College and Graduate School Papers, 1933-1948 (Box 23, Folder 1)
  - Grades for University of Chicago Course – Religion and Science, 1991 (Box 23, Folder 2)
  - Grades for University of Chicago Course, 1992 (Box 23, Folder 3)
  - Recommendations – De Souza, Rowena, and Pedraja, Luis, 1993 (Box 23, Folder 4)
  - Recommendations – Himes, Michael, 1997 (Box 23, Folder 5)
  - Recommendations – Kok, Peter, 1996 (Box 23, Folder 6)
  - Recommendations – Pasewark, Kyle, 1993-1997 (Box 23, Folder 7)
  - Recommendations – Pool, Jeff B., 1986 (Box 23, Folder 8)
  - Recommendations – Redwine, Michael, 1997 (Box 23, Folder 9)
  - Recommendations – Rike, Jennifer, 1997 (Box 23, Folder 10)
  - Recommendations – Sapp, Gregory, 1996 (Box 23, Folder 11)
  - Recommendations – Scharf, Uwe, 1995 (Box 23, Folder 12)
  - Recommendations – Simmons, Stephen, 1997 (Box 23, Folder 13)
  - Recommendations – Stenger, Mary Ann, and Lamm, Julia, 1994 (Box 23, Folder 14)
  - Recommendations – Yerkes, James, 1995 (Box 23, Folder 15)